Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series XI: Holy Father and Gloria, 1985-1991; 479173
  - Footage: O'Higgins Park, Santiago: Protests at Pope's Mass, 1987; cuid18276; 467216 (Box 43, Cassette ref837, Box 97, Dvd ref837)
    This video begins with footage of violent clashes between the police and protestors at O'Higgins Park in Santiago, Chile where Pope John Paul II delivered Mass to a large crowd in 1987. The footage shows protestors building makeshift barriers and throwing objects while police try to disperse them. The footage focuses primarily on the crowd, and does not show the Pope speaking, although he can be heard through a loudspeaker. The video features several on-the-street interviews: one with a man opposed to the protests, one with a local journalist, and one with a young protester. The end of this video also features an interview with exiled Chilean Socialist leader Clodomiro Almeyda. In the interview Almeyda discusses why he chose to return to Chile during the Pope's visit to the country.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:02:33.
  - Footage: "Chile, Students, Gloria", 1987; cuid790; 479714 (Box 60, Cassette ref1367, Box 98, Dvd ref1367)
    This video features interviews with three different groups of students in Chile. Estela Bravo asks the students, who are from middle and upper-class schools, about their opinions of Chilean President Augusto Pinochet, Pope John Paul II's visit, and the attack on Carmen Gloria Quintana. Students from the various groups express different opinions on these topics, and many of the students who come from upper-class households express their support of Pinochet. They argue that the people protesting his government are mistaken and supporters of terrorism. Several students express their admiration for Pinochet, and contend that he saved the country from communism. Other students express their dislike of Pinochet, and contend that the students who support him are uninformed and are not in a position to understand the political situation of the country.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:57:28.
  - Footage: Chilean Boy and the Police, 1987 March 4; cuid18277; 479720 (Box 60, Cassette ref1373, Box 98, Dvd ref1373)
    This video begins with footage of a mother trying to talk to Chilean police about her son. She explains that she heard that her son, who was 9 years old at the time the footage was recorded, was injured by police after they chased him into a house. The woman attempts to find out what happened to her son and where he was taken, but the police do not give her any information. The video then focuses on the house where the boy was attacked. The family in the house explains that they police chased the boy, broke down their door, and hit the young boy in the head causing him to bleed significantly. Several of the children and adults in the house describe witnessing the event. They also talk about police treatment of the poor and substandard living conditions in their community.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:18.
  - Footage: "Pinochet greets Pope at the airport", 1987; cuid18278; 479552 (Box 52, Cassette ref1210)
  - Footage: Rojas Grave and Interview with son of Orlando Letelier, 1987; cuid389; 467243 (Box 39, Cassette ref810, Box 95, Dvd ref810)
    Juan Pablo Letelier was the son of Orlando Letelier. Orlando Letelier was a Chilean diplomat under the government of Salvador Allende. He left Chile as a refugee of the dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet, and was assassinated by Pinochet's secret police in Washington D.C. in 1976.
    This video mostly features an interview with Juan Pablo Letelier. The first few seconds of the video contain footage of the grave of Chilean dissident Rodrigo Andres Rojas de Negri. It quickly changes to an interview with Letelier, which begins with a discussion about his early life and his father's assassination. He discusses leaving Chile when he was 3 years old, and returning to Chile later in life. He also talks about his involvement in leftist political movements in Chile and his participations in Chile's Socialist Youth. He discusses the significance of the visit of Pope John Paul II in 1987, and the 1989 general elections. Letelier talks at length about the political climate in Chile at the end of the 1980s discussing the country's transition to democracy and the influence of youth activism. The video quality is poor in many places.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:58.
  - Footage: College Stadium (the Pope speaking and Carmen Gloria in the audience) and Cemetery, 1987; cuid18279; 479715 (Box 67, Cassette ref1368)
  - Footage: Police Brutality, 1985 September 4; cuid18280; 479716 (Box 67, Cassette ref1369)
  - Footage: Carmen Gloria Quintana Complete Visit Jail, circa 1987; cuid18281; 479717 (Box 60, Cassette ref1370, Box 98, Dvd ref1370)
    This video features footage of Carmen Gloria Quintana attempting to gain entry into a jail in Chile to meet with political prisoners. A spokesman for Quintana explains she is there to express her solidarity with prisoners. The bulk of the footage features a crowd waiting outside the jail hoping to gain entry. This video duplicates content contained on video ref1361.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:03.
  - Footage: "Carmen Gloria in victory", 1987; cuid18282; 467242 (Box 39, Cassette ref811, Box 97, Dvd ref811)
    This video begins with brief footage of two Chilean youths at a mural memorializing the attack on Carmen Gloria Quintana and Rodrigo Rojas who were burned by Chilean military police in 1986. The video then changes to footage of Quintana arriving at a rally in her honor. Much of this footage features shots of the crowd gathered in anticipation of Quintana's arrival. At minute 13:00 Quintana addresses the crowd and describes her encounter with the military, in which she and Rojas were doused with gasoline and then lit on fire. At the time of her speech, she explains that it has been 10 months since the event and notes that she has been left badly disfigured and Rojas has died.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:09.
  - Footage: March Final Against Torture, 1987 February 4; cuid18283; 479718 (Box 60, Carton ref1371, Box 98, Dvd ref1371)
    The beginning of this video features an interview with a man and a woman in a church in Chile. They discuss their involvement in the resistance movement against the Pinochet government and the violence they have witnessed in the country. The interview focuses on the government's use of torture against citizens. The woman shares specific examples of torture used against Chilean citizens, discuss police interrogation methods, and describes the psychological effects of state-sponsored violence. At minute 12:00 the video features a demonstration against the government, and protestors can be seen clashing briefly with the police. Bravo interviews members of the crowd about why they are at the protest, and about their expectations for the upcoming 1987 visit of Pope John Paul II.
  - National Stadium / Pope Compilation, 1987; cuid18284; 467503 (Box 23, Cassette ref550)
  - "Pope, Chile, Street, Carmen Gloria, Funeral Rodrigo," and Others, 1987; cuid18285; 479710 (Box 60, Cassette ref1363)
  - Carmen Gloria " Ernesto's Copy", 1987; cuid18286; 467212 (Box 43, Cassette ref878)
  - "2 Carmen Gloria Completa", 1987; cuid18287; 467800 (Box 11, Cassette ref253)
  - "El Santo Padre y la Gloria", 1987; cuid18288; 467423 (Box 32, Cassette ref630)
  - "El Santo Padre y la Gloria", 1987; cuid18289; 467369 (Box 31, Cassette ref684)
  - "TV Espanola Programa Editado - Pinochet - the Pope - Chile - Carmen Gloria", 1987; cuid18290; 467334 (Box 38, Cassette ref719)
  - "Hotel Capri - press conference - Estela Bravo - Juan Vilar", circa 1987; cuid18291; 467333 (Box 38, Cassette ref720)
  - "Torture photos - Pinochet speech", circa 1987; cuid18292; 467327 (Box 38, Cassette ref726)
  - "Pepe Carrasco CNN Pinochet", circa 1986; cuid18293; 467251 (Box 39, Cassette ref802, Box 97, Dvd ref802)
    Jose Humberto "Pepe" Carrasco Tapia (1943-1986) was a Chilean journalist opposed to the military dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet. He was assassinated on September 7, 1986.
    This video features an assortment of footage filmed in Chile around 1986. It begins with footage of protesters clashing with military police. It then changes to shots of newspaper headlines announcing the arrival of socialist politician Clodomiro Almeyda. At minute 9:29 the footage changes to edits of a CNN Atlanta news report on the political climate in Chile. The footage features several segments which focus on a failed national strike, the death of journalist José Carrasco, and the dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet. After the CNN report ends the video features additional raw footage of protests, funerals, government events, and a short speech by Pinochet denouncing communists in the country. The end of the video features footage of an impoverished community.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:01:59.
  - "Carmen Gloria - Final Victory - Cemetery", 1987 May 4; cuid18294; 467250 (Box 39, Cassette ref803)
  - "Chile Carmen Gloria", 1987; cuid18295; 467217 (Box 43, Cassette ref836)
  - "Film festival - Homage to Estela Bravo for Holy Father and Gloria"(about Bravo), 1987; cuid18296; 467328 (Box 38, Cassette ref725)
  - "Photos - Carmen Gloria - the Pope speaks - Dibuyos (drawings)", 1987; cuid18297; 467330 (Box 38, Cassette ref723)
  - Carmen Gloria Quintana Arriving in Chile / Allemand, Maria Olga: Interview, 1987; cuid18298; 467332 (Box 38, Cassette ref721, Box 97, Dvd ref721)
    This video begins with footage of Carmen Gloria Quintana arriving in Chile in 1987. She is greeted by crowds and speaks to reporters. At minute 5:00 the video changes to an interview with Chilean photographer Maria Olga Allemand. In the interview Allemand talks about being shot while photographing a demonstration. She describes the event, and the people who helped her immediately after she was shot. She discusses the support she received from her community and her desire to continue working as a photographer despite the risk of being injured again. The end of the video changes back to footage of Quintana, and features portion of a speech she delivered to a village in Chile.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:06.
  - "Carmen Gloria Bump", 1987; cuid18299; 467220 (Box 43, Cassette ref833, Box 97, Dvd ref833)
    This video contains various segments featuring Carmen Gloria Quintana in Chile. Segments include footage of Quintana speaking at rallies, traveling through crowds, attending mass, attempting to speak to political prisoners, and visiting the grave of her friend Rodrigo Rojas. The video also shows short clips of demonstrations on the streets of Chile and a speech by Pope John Paul II. Segments that appear on this tape are duplicated on other videos contained in this series.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:39:13.
  - "Event at National Stadium", 1987; cuid18300; 467245 (Box 39, Cassette ref808)
  - "Carmen Gloria in church door", 1987; cuid18301; 467241 (Box 39, Cassette ref812)
- Series XII: The Hour of the People, 1985-1988; 479648
  This 39-minute film Hour of the People (La Hor del Pueblo ) documents the Uruguay's return to democracy, following a peaceful transition from a military dictatorship that ruled the country between 1973 and 1985. This series includes copies of the full-length documentary, as well as interview footage with Uruguayan Communist Party leader Jaime Perez.
  - La Hora del Pueblo (Master), 1985; cuid782; 479649 (Box 57, Cassette ref1306, Box 96, Dvd ref1306)
    This video contains a full version of the short documentary Hour of the People (La Hor del Pueblo).
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:39:56.
  - La Hora del Pueblo, 1985; cuid788; 479650 (Box 57, Cassette ref1307, Box 96, Dvd ref1307)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:39:37.
  - The Hour of the People, 1985; cuid783; 479685 (Box 59, Cassette ref1342, Box 96, Dvd ref1342)
    This video contains a complete version of the short film Hour of the People (La Hor del Pueblo). Video quality of this recording is intermittently poor.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:54:45.
  - Perez, Jaime: Interview, circa 1985; cuid784; 479651 (Box 57, Cassette ref1308, Box 96, Dvd ref1308)
    Jaime Perez was a Jewish union leader in Uruguay. He was imprisoned for 10 years by the government of Uruguay because of his leadership in the Communist Party of the Uruguay.
    In this interview Uruguayan politician Jaime Perez begins by discussing his travels to Cuba in the early 1970s and meeting Fidel Castro. He then talks about his 10-year imprisonment in Uruguay by the country's military dictatorship. He describes Uruguay's transition to democracy and the influence of the country's foreign debt on that process. He explains that he is optimistic about the transition to democracy, but contends that the process has just begun and that the country has a long history of repression and disappearance of political dissidents that needs to be addressed. At the end of the interview he expresses his gratitude to Castro and Cuba for supporting the Communist Party in Uruguay and its fight against the military dictatorship.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:28:06.
  - La Hora del Pueblo, 1988 October 26; cuid18302; 467214 (Box 43, Cassette ref839)
- Series XIII: Mandela and Fidel, 2013; 590489
  This series contains a copy of the Bravo documentary Mandel and Fidel, which documents the friendship between Nelson Mandela and Fidel Castro. No clips or raw footage associated with this film is included in the series. Instead, much of the footage used in this 30-minute documentary was drawn from earlier films including Namibia: The Last Colony (1990), Mandela in Cuba (1991), and Fidel The Untold Story (2000).
  The film begins with Nelson Mandela's attendance at the Namibian independence celebrations in March of 1990, a month following his release from prison. He meets with Cuban officials and expresses his gratitude for Cuba's assistance in the war in Angola and for its role in the Namibian war of independence. The next year Mandela visits Cuba. The documentary follows the relationship for several more years including Castro's attendance at Mandela's inauguration in 1994 and Fidel's visit to Robben Island to see where Mandela was imprisoned.
  - Mandela and Fidel, 2013; cuid18303; 590490 (Box 73, Dvd 4)
    This is a full-length version of the film Mandela and Fidel.
- Series XIV: Mandela in Cuba, 1991; 479077
  In 1991 Nelson Mandela visited Cuba during a tour to Latin American. Then President of the African National Congress, Mandela used the tour to lobby countries like Brazil, Mexico, and Venezuela to maintain sanctions against South Africa's white minority government, and support a national unity government in Pretoria. Mandela made a three-day stop in Cuba during the tour to meet with Fidel Castro. Mandela and Castro had never met before the visit, but the two shared admiration for one another stemming from Cuba's support of Angolan and Namibian independence.
  Mandela in Cuba documents Nelson Mandela's three-day visit to Cuba in July of 1991. He attended the celebrations marking the 38th anniversary of the 1953 attack on the Moncada garrison. The series contains a full-length copy of the documentary and footage shot during Mandela's visit. The footage shows speeches and events surrounding the visit, as well as clips of Nelson and Winnie Mandela touring historical sites in Cuba.
  - Mandela in Cuba, 1991; cuid18304; 479078 (Box 71, Cassette ref947, Box 85, Dvd ref947)
    This is a full-length version of the film Mandela in Cuba. This film is in English.
  - Mandela in Cuba, 1991; cuid18305; 467380 (Box 93, Cassette ref673, Box 83, Dvd ref673)
  - Mandela, Nelson: Press Conference in Cuba, 1991; cuid18306; 467912 (Box 5, Cassette ref141, Box 77, Dvd ref141)
    This footage includes about ten minutes of questions and answers at a press conference. Mandela's responses to questions can be heard clearly, but many of the reporters' questions and translations are difficult to hear. In this recording Estela Bravo asks Mandela a question, which can be heard clearly. Additionally, there are places where imaging is poor and scenes are difficult to view.
  - "Mandela Press Conference in Havana", 1991; cuid18307; 467896 (Box 7, Cassette ref157)
  - Fidel and Mandela in Matanzas: Footage at beginning of rally, 1991 July 26; cuid18308; 467350 (Box 87, Cassette ref703, Box 83, Dvd ref703)
    This footage documents the early parts of a July 1991 rally at Matanzas with Nelson Mandela, honoring the 38th anniversary of the Moncada assault that led to Fidel Castro's seizure of power. The footage begins with the singing of the Cuban anthem and an introduction to the event. During the event there are introductions of notable attendees including Daniel Ortega of Nicaragua. Castro speaks to each of the individuals. The footage also shows other Cuban dignitaries who attended the event including Raul Castro and Juan Almeida. This recording is in Spanish.
  - Fidel and Mandela in Matanzas: Speech, Fidel Castro, 1991 July 26; cuid18309; 467299 (Box 94, Cassette ref754, Box 83, Dvd ref754)
    This footage features a speech by Fidel Castro at Matanzas during Nelson Mandela's 1991 trip to Cuba. The speech is in Spanish.
  - Fidel and Mandela: Speech in Matanzas, 1991 July 26; cuid18310; 467811 (Box 5, Cassette ref242, Box 77, Dvd ref242)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:00.
  - Footage of Portion of Fidel Speech, 1991 July 26; cuid18311; 467916 (Box 5, Cassette ref137, Box 77, Dvd ref137)
    The location and date of this footage is unclear. The original box annotation was "Fidel and Mandela" although Mandela does not appear in the footage. This was possibly filmed at the Matanzas event in 1991 celebrating the anniversary of the Moncada uprising.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:17:52.
  - Mandela (brief speech); Primarily a speech by Manchado Ventura, 1991 July 26; cuid18312; 467900 (Box 5, Cassette ref153, Box 77, Dvd ref153)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:17:00.
  - Mandela and Fidel in Old Havana, 1991; cuid18313; 467842 (Box 5, Cassette ref211, Box 77, Dvd ref211)
  - Mandela touring museum in Havana, 1991; cuid18314; 467621 (Box 92, Cassette ref432, Box 81, Dvd ref432)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:18:00.
  - Meeting with Mandela, 1991; cuid18315; 467379 (Box 93, Cassette ref674, Box 83, Dvd ref674)
    Mandela talks about Cuban assistance in Angola and also about support of the Sandinistas in Nicaragua.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:08:00.
  - Speech footage: Fidel and Mandela in Matanzas, 1991 July 26; cuid18316; 477177 (Box 70, Cassette ref918, Box 85, Dvd ref918)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:47.
  - Winnie and Nelson Mandela Old Havana, 1991; cuid18317; 467911 (Box 5, Cassette ref142, Box 77, Dvd ref142)
    This clip shows Nelson and Winnie Mandela on a tour of Old Havana, which includes a trip to an African museum. The footage shows them speaking to various people, signing a guest book, and discussing their desire to contribute South African artifacts to the museum. In some places, the sound is lost and images are scrambled, but the footage is easily viewable.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:16:00.
- Series XV: Mandela Visits Jamaica, 1991; 590321
  This series contains full-length versions and raw footage from the documentary Mandela Visits Jamaica, which chronicles Nelson Mandela's visit to Jamaica during his 1991 tour of the Caribbean and Latin America. Footage in this series includes scenes of crowds waiting to meet Nelson and Winnie Mandela, Mandela at speaking events, scenes from the Jamaican Parliament, and background footage.
  - Mandela in Jamaica, 1991; cuid18318; 467376 (Box 93, Cassette ref677, Box 83, Dvd ref677)
    This is a full-length version of the film Mandela in Jamaica. This recording contains additional footage after the credits.
  - Mandela Visits Jamaica, 1991; TW_TAM_616_ER_9
  - Mandela Visits Jamaica /Mandela in Cuba, 1991; cuid18319; 467422 (Box 93, Cassette ref631, Box 82, Dvd ref631)
    This full-length version of Mandela Visits Jamaica appears to have been taped over a copy of Mandela in Cuba (which is longer but ends abruptly during a Fidel Castro speech).
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:11:00.
  - Footage of Mandela in Jamaica, 1991; cuid18320; 467430 (Box 93, Cassette ref623, Box 82, Dvd ref623)
    This tape contains footage of people lining up for Nelson and Winnie Mandela's appearance at a speaking event at the University of the West Indies. It then cuts to footage of the Jamaican Parliament welcoming Mandela who addressed its members.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:51:05.
  - Footage of Mandela in Jamaica ("Assemblia Popular"), 1991; cuid18321; 467915 (Box 5, Cassette ref138, Box 77, Dvd ref138)
    The first ten minutes consists of scenes in a large chamber with no sound; Fidel enters and is seated. After a few minutes of test pattern, there is sound and a picture of the Mandelas (and Jorge Risquet) at airport boarding a plane (en route to Jamaica per Estela Bravo). There is sound and people speaking with each other but the sound of the plane engine drowns out the conversations. There are many close-ups of the various people in Mandela's entourage. Finally, the last few minutes return to a chamber filled with people but no sound.
- Series XVI: The Marielitos, 1982; 479231
  Released in 1983, The Marielitos (Los Marielitos) tells the story of Cubans who left the island from the port of Mariel in 1980. In the documentary, Estela Bravo interviews individuals living in Miami who were part of the Mariel boatlift two years after their arrival in the United States. She talks with them about their expectations for life in the United States and their experiences since their arrival.
  In the wake of an economic downturn in 1980, approximately 10,000 Cubans tried to leave Cuba and seek asylum in the Peruvian embassy. As a result, the Cuban government announced that anyone who wanted to leave the country could do so. In a joint agreement between the United States and Cuba, some 125,000 refugees left the Cuban port of Mariel bound for the United States in what came to be known as the Mariel Boatlift. Cubans who traveled to the US as part of the boatlift came to be known as Marielitos.
  Estela Bravo's documentary about the boatlift, The Marielitos, won the International Organization of Journalists 1st Prize at the 1984 Leipzig Film Festival and a Patria Society Award at the Moscow Film Festival.
  - Los Marielitos, circa 1982; cuid390; 479640 (Box 57, Cassette ref1297, Box 96, Dvd ref1297)
    This video contains a complete version of the documentary Los Marielitos.
  - Los Marielitos, 1982; 2016.025; 593075 (Reel ref2169)
  - Los Marielitos, "Spanish, Cassette #24" - Possible full-length feature, circa 1982; cuid18322; 479232 (Box 61, Cassette ref973)
  - Los Marielitos, "English, Cassette #23 DV #5" Possible full-length feature, circa 1982; cuid18323; 479235 (Box 45, Cassette ref974)
  - Los Marielitos, "Spanish, no subtitles" Possible full-length feature, circa 1982; cuid18324; 479641 (Box 57, Cassette ref1298)
  - Footage: Scenes of Camp Mosquito Marielitos, circa 1982; cuid18325; 467361 (Box 5, Cassette ref692, Box 83, Dvd ref692)
    El Mosquito was a holding area for Cubans waiting to join the Mariel boatlift.
  - Footage - Families of rafters, Church World Service, circa 1982; cuid18326; 467487 (Box 87, Cassette ref566, Box 82, Dvd ref566)